Maybe you've tried vibe coding and
cursor a few months ago, but it just
didn't stick for you. Or maybe you're
still skeptical of the idea that we as
professional software developers should
be letting AI write most of our code.
Well, I'm telling you that right now I'm
seeing a real shift in how vibe coding
or building software with AI is
happening at the professional level. In
this video, I'm going to show you the
new workflow in Cursor and other tools
like it that's taking vibe coding from
hacky or fun side projects to the
professional level on real projects,
real products. It's changing the way
that we build and it's time that we
embrace it. You know, I've been building
professionally for 20 years, and I want
to tell you why I'm actually excited and
optimistic about this new way of
building software, which I believe is
becoming the new norm. So, even if
you're skeptical or even if you feel
like you've been slow to adopt these new
AI tools, I want you to hear this. Look,
vibe coding for professionals does not
mean that AI is coming for our jobs or
our business. And it does not mean that
we're losing our craft and what we love
most about creating and designing and
building great software products. In
fact, it's the opposite. If you're
experienced in building software and you
take pride in your taste and in your
craft, then you're at a huge advantage
in this new way of building with AI at
the professional level. And if you're
earlier in your career, as our industry
is shifting to this new way of building
with AI, you're at an advantage, too,
because you don't need to navigate the
transition from the old way and the old
workflows of building software to the
new way that folks who've been around a
few years need to deal with. By the way,
my channel here on YouTube is focusing
on building with AI. So, if you're
thinking about this, leave your top
questions in the comments below and make
sure that you're subscribed. Also, I'll
be teaching a workshop on this coming
up. So, leave a comment and I'll make
sure that you get in on that as well.
Now, when it comes to building software
with AI in these last few years, there
have been about three major step changes
in our workflow. And I think that we're
now entering the third of these changes.
I'll get to that in a minute. But how we
got here is we started with you know tab
code completion. GitHub copilot was
probably the first mass adoption tool
for this where you know you're writing a
line of code and you see the line
complete itself or a whole method sort
of write itself out automatically with
the help of AI then you can hit tab to
accept it. That was, you know, a few
years ago now and I remember when it
came in and that was like a wow moment.
Like this is a lot better than
handtyping every single character in our
codebase. Then agent mode really took
off and of course this has been
popularized with cursor and windurf. And
I think this is more or less where we
are now. It's certainly where I have
been myself in terms of my day-to-day
building software workflow. You know,
I'm finding that I'm spending most, if
not all, of my time in agent mode in
cursor, writing prompts into the chat
window and letting AI write most of the
code in my codebase. And this is
definitely a level up from, you know,
tabbing through these code completions
line by line or, you know, copying and
pasting code snippets from chat GPT or
claude into my codebase because of
course tools like cursor are integrated
with my entire codebase and they can
make edits to multiple files at once.
And so already we're doing a lot of
building with AI. And that's certainly
what my day-to-day building workflow has
looked like up until now. And I'm
building stuff faster than I have in
years past. And I actually think better.
I can be more ambitious about the types
of things that I build. But you know
what? Now that I've gotten used to this
agent mode style of building with AI,
I'm noticing some
inefficiencies. I'm noticing that it
actually seems like more work than it
should be. You know, for me, as someone
who is experienced in full stack
software design development, I do want
to spoon feed the AI with detailed
prompts. So, I'm actually spending a lot
of time writing and rewriting and
drafting just the prompt text that I'm
dropping into the cursor chat window.
It's still more efficient because the AI
can build a lot more than I could
myself. But I'm starting to feel how
it's cumbersome and time consuming and
physically tired. And that's why right
now I am starting to embrace this new
third way of building with AI. And I'm
starting to think of this like
taskdirected development. It's sort of
like the new TDD, you know, testdriven
development. And tests actually really
do have their place in this new
workflow. maybe even more so than they
did in years past. But at a high level,
this new norm or this new current way of
building software is what I like to
think of as taskdirected development.
Now, there are some new tools popping up
like taskmaster and Ryan Carson recently
published some cursor rules that help to
manage this highle workflow and I'm
going to show you these here in just a
second. But you know, no matter which
tooling you're using, I think the
highlevel workflow or the process for
building out complex professional pieces
of software is the same in this new way
of doing it. So the concept is this. We
start with a PRD or a project
requirements document. And this is where
we as the experienced human full stack
designer developer, this is where most
of our experience and the stamp that
we're going to put on our work comes
into play. The PRD is the road map. It's
the detail of the project that we are
going to be working on. Then we turn
that PRD into a list of highle tasks.
That's like your road map for this
project from from idea to shipped. Then
we want to break down those tasks into
smaller subtasks. This sounds just like
a typical project that you might manage
or direct a junior developer on. And
that's exactly what this whole concept
is modeled after. And then of course the
AI is going to execute each tasks one by
one in order taking dependencies into
account while we the experienced
developer can oversee and approve and
course correct and really manage the
whole project from start to finish. So
this is what vibe coding at the
professional level is looking like.
We're moving away from spoon feeding
cursor in agent mode with writing
prompts all day long and we're moving
toward a more cohesive end to end
project where we are frontloading most
of our creativity and effort and work
and time on crafting a really
wellwritten PRD project requirement
document and then you know building it
out into a task list and then having the
AI execute our project while we oversee
direct and it tracks its progress all
the way through. This way reduces
mistakes big time. It reduces those
endless loops that we go through, you
know, fixing and undoing a lot of, you
know, code slop that comes from, you
know, just prompting cursor randomly all
day. It brings order to the chaos that
is kind of vibe coding and and building
with AI. And frankly, I'm finding it's a
more enjoyable and relaxed and focused
and actually creative approach to
building out our software ideas. Okay,
let me show you what this is actually
looking like in practice. Now, I'm going
to show you two different ways of doing
this. One is using Taskmaster. That is a
new tool that's getting really popular
right now. It's a really interesting
tool, really powerful. I'm going to walk
through what this looks like, but I
actually like a lighterwe version of
this which was created by Ryan Carson.
It's a couple of cursor rules files and
a process for using those. I'm liking
this better and I'm going to show you
both because this is something that I
could see myself really embracing and
and adapting. I think that's a really
important part of this as well. But I'm
going to start with Taskmaster so you
can, you know, follow the instructions
and get it all installed. I already have
it installed on my system. I started up
a new project. This is a fresh Ruby on
Rails application I like to build in the
Rails space. So I'm going to start by
initializing Taskmaster on this project.
Taskmaster init. And this is going to do
a bunch of things. It's going to install
this Taskmaster folder. So I'm just
going to use these default settings that
they have. Now one more thing is you
will need to put in your API keys for at
least one of the models. I put in my
anthropic API key into both the cursor
MCP JSON as well as the ENV file in my
project. When I installed this, it also
added an
MCP to cursor. You can see this
taskmaster AI that's enabled. So what
that essentially means is that when I'm
prompting incursor, I could just use
natural language to trigger any of these
tasks that are built into taskmaster,
including the first one, which is going
to be generating the actual PRD
document. So, this first step in this
new workflow is really the only part
where I'm actually handwriting a bunch
of content and ideas in in a raw text
format because it's going to take my raw
idea that I'm going to prompt and then
it's going to build a nicely formed,
highly detailed PRD document. So,
Taskmaster provides this example
PRD.ext. Let me show you that. Um, and
this is like the the structure, you
know, of of how it should be built out.
This is sort of like a template. So, I'm
going to actually give it, you know, the
prompt for what I want to build here.
And let's, as a simple example, we're
going to do a very simple to-do list
application. Have a prompt ready to go
here. So, all this is, and I just like
personally wrote this. This is like a
simple idea for a to-do list
application. couple bullet points of of
like the the main features that I wanted
to have, a couple notes about what type
of project I I've already set up. Now,
I'm asking it to I want to create a I
want you to create a PRD. And since I'm
using Taskmaster, I'm going to say using
example
PRD.ext. I might not even need that
since I have that in the context window
and cursor, but I'm just going to
include it anyway. And I'm going to go
ahead and have it do that. And so now,
you know, the claude essentially, but
Taskmaster is using this format or this
template. It's taking this idea and it's
turning it into a highly detailed PRD
document. Okay, that's all set. And here
it is. Here's the
PRD.ext. And you know, it's got like
core features, descriptions, and you
know, some like functional and user
experience notes, key user flows, UI, UX
considerations, technical architecture.
So I can actually go through this and
again like as an experienced developer I
can go through and I can find the points
that I think are incorrect or I want to
you know craft or re rewrite. Like for
example it's saying use Rails 7.1. Of
course I want to be using 8, you know,
and there's going to be a bunch of other
you know details in here that maybe I
don't necessarily agree with or I want
to be done differently. So that's where
I can put my stamp on things. All right.
Next with taskmaster I can have it parse
my PRD and turn it into a highle list of
tasks. So actually the the chat is
already asking me if I want to proceed
with that step and it's saying would you
like me to run the parse PRD tool to
automatically generate your initial
development tasks and yes I do. So I'll
just say yes. Easy enough. It noticed
that I updated it to Rails 8.
Interesting. Okay. So it finished that
and now should be able to run
taskmaster list. Okay, so here we go. We
have this highle list. It gave us 12
tasks and it's telling us what the next
recommended task is, which is the first
one. So let's take a look at this list
some more. We've got status. In fact,
the first step is already done because
I've already set up the Rails project.
It has prioritized the the tasks. It
also set up task dependencies, which is
really interesting. And it doesn't yet
have this complexity score because I
haven't run that yet. Uh, I can run
taskmaster help to see what the what the
possible what the commands are. So, I'm
going to do
taskmaster analyze complexity. This is
going to actually have it look through
all of the tasks in my list and do some
research on the internet to find out
like what's actually involved in all
these individual tasks. Now, personally,
this is one of those things about
Taskmaster that I it's not really
clicking with me yet. This feels a
little bit like it's too much. And I'm
going to show you the other way of doing
it using some cursor rules that Ryan
Carson put together which I really like.
I'm going to show that next. But I just
want to show Taskmaster here. So let's
look at our task list again. And now
that we've done the the complexity
analysis, we have these green, yellow,
and red dots here. And that's, you know,
how complex is each task, right? You
know the next step in this workflow is
to take our highle tasks and turn them
into subtasks. Now really we should do
this for like all of the tasks. So you
could do something like spand all.
That's probably what you would do in for
a normal project. In this case let's
just do one of them. Item number seven.
That's an that's a red dot. That means
it's highly complex. That'll be
implementation of the drag and drop
functionality. We want to break that one
out into multiple subtasks. So, I'm
going to do
taskmaster expand
ID seven. That's, you know, because
we're on row number seven there. Okay.
So, that's done. And once again, I'm
going to list out my tasks. Oh, I forgot
to do um I know it's with subtasks,
maybe. As you can see, I'm I'm new to
playing with with Taskmaster, but yeah,
here you go. So, you've got your main
tasks and then subtasks, you know, 7.1,
7.2, 7.3, and so on. It tells us, you
know, here's the recommended next task,
and I can instruct the AI to proceed
with the next tasks or even proceed with
multiple tasks according to our task
list and the dependencies and the
priority order. Just to show you what
else is happening under the hood here.
So, underneath tasks, we've got these
text documents, and these are sort of
like the actual instructions that the
that the AI will will have for each
individual task. And this starts to show
you some of the power in terms of the
workflow, right? Because normally I
would, you know, manually write these
prompts, like spoon feeding these
prompts one by one, but now it's all
planned out in these pre-written task
instructions. So now all I really need
to do is say like these proceed with the
first task. So it's going straight into
task two because task one was actually
already finished, you know, like setting
up the the Rails project. And I also
have my cursor set up for in cursor
settings. You go to
features. You want to enable auto run.
They used to call this yolo mode. Now
it's called auto run. Check that box.
They're going to show you a little
warning that it's kind of scary. Don't
worry. you do want to go ahead with that
because every one of these little tasks
that the cursor agent is doing, you
know, instead of needing to approve or
let it run, you know, tasks in the
terminal and stuff like that, it can
just auto run those without me needing
to do anything. So, I can sort of like
watch its progress here and I can see
there are already some files being
created. It's building out the task
model. It found a little syntax error in
something. It's checking that and it's
going to fix that. It's trying a simpler
approach. So it looks like something is
going on. Okay, it got that sorted out
and task number two is complete. All
right, so let's look at our task list
again. And so now we see some progress
has been made there. And now you can
see, you know, task number two is done.
The rest are still pending. And that's
basically the the workflow with using
Taskmaster. Now it's pretty cool. This
is a really powerful tool. I could see
why so many people are getting pretty
excited about this. But I'll be honest,
I'm finding this to be a little bit
much. It's it's sort of like a lot of
tooling really. I just want to get to
the building. That's why I really
appreciate this project that Ryan Carson
put together. Um, and he shared this on
GitHub. It's basically like AI dev tasks
for cursor. And all it really is are
these three cursor rules files. And it's
the same exact strategy or the same
high-level workflow which is create the
PRD, generate tasks from the PRD, and
then process the task list. So, it's a
much lighter weight version. And I
actually like it for that reason, but
also because I could see places where I
want to adapt this to my style and my
specific needs and the types of products
and projects that I'm working on. Right?
So, yeah, let's play around with this a
little bit. I'm going to go into this
other fresh new project. And I have
those three files installed under, you
know, the cursor folder under rules. And
then we have the create PRD uh MDC file,
generate tasks file, and process task
lists. So, right now, these are exactly
as Ryan Carson had put them together.
Now, I'm going to be tweaking these
quite a bit as I go forward in my
projects because I can already see some
places where I want to sort of build out
and optimize my workflow and as I learn
more, I'm going to be posting more
videos about that. But it does work
really well sort of like right out of
the box. So, we're going to start with
this create PRD process and it's very
similar to before. We have the create
PRD cursor rules in the context here.
I'm going to paste in the same prompt
that I pasted in last time for
Taskmaster where, you know, I'm saying I
want to build out a simple to-do list
application that has these features.
Here's the here's the checklist, some
information about it, and let's see. Do
I need to actually reference anything? I
don't think so because we already have
the create PRD instructions here. So,
we're going to go ahead and have it do
that and see what happens. Okay, so the
way that this one is set up is sort of
interesting. instead of going straight
to to creating the the PRD just based on
my raw prompt. I I kind of like this. It
has clarifying questions, right? So, the
process for creating a PRD is first ask
clarifying questions, you know, like
what is the problem and the goal? Who's
the target user? What are the user
stories for this? So, it took my raw
prompt and it's asking those questions
sort of adapted for for my use case.
Now, I I do sort of think that a lot of
these questions are a little it's a
little much, you know, like but some of
them are are really kind of functional
and I can see all this being really
useful. So, I'm just going to answer
like some of them and give it a little
bit more information. And, you know, I
really don't need to type much. I'm just
going to, you know, go based on the
numbers. So one let's do to expand
because it sort of gave me a few
options. Now normally I would put a lot
more detail and thought into these
questions. Data persistence I want to
use SQ light for this a very simple
database. So I'm just like answering
these questions trying to be as as quick
as possible. But you know what AI is
great at just understanding what I mean
because it asked these questions and and
you know I'm giving it my direct answer.
So just nice and easy for me as the
product owner and the project manager on
this to just answer answer the questions
and let's get a nice fully detailed PRD
written out for us. So it's going ahead
and it's creating that PRD. Okay, so
here it is. I'm going to accept it. It
placed this in tasks and then PRD to-do
list because this is like a to-do list
application. That's what it named it.
It's all in markdown format. We've got
the user stories. We've got some goals.
We've got some functional requirements.
It's all very organized, nice and easy
to read. I'm actually finding that this
again, it's just easier for me to read,
which means it's easier for me to go in
and make edits to it. And again, that's
where most of the work and the time and
the effort should be going in as
professional designers, developers,
product managers, product owners. This
is the most important step. This is
where we are putting our stamp on it
before we you know delegate it to our
junior developer. In this case, our
junior developer happens to be an AI
agent in cursor. All right. So that's
good to go. So the next step is going to
be to uh please generate tasks and use
the generate tasks cursor rules. I think
that's all it should need. So going to
use that and it's going to follow the
instructions here in generate tasks
which is to start by creating this basic
tople list of tasks. This is a markdown
checklist. So unlike taskmaster where it
all happens, you know, like in the
terminal, this is an actual markdown
file that lives in my project under
under the tasks folder. So as we go
along, it's going to, you know, check
these off with X's. So it generated a
highle list of tasks based on the PRD.
And so again, I can look at these, I can
make edits to them, but it's asking if I
want to just press say go to proceed.
meaning go means it's going to just go
ahead with creating those subtasks. So
it you again like that whole system and
process and workflow is already built in
to these rules. So all I need to do is
say go. All right. So now our sort of
road map has been all built out. As you
can see we have a list of relevant files
that it's going to build throughout the
course of this project. It added some
notes and then of course here is our
task lists. And now every one of those
tasks has like you know 2.1 2.2 2.3 3.1
3.2 3.3 and so on. So we have a much
more detailed road map and and task list
to get going on. Next we're just going
to have it, you know, run through these
tasks following our process task list
instruction. So, I'm going to add that
process task list to the to the context
here. And I'm going to say let's proceed
with the first task. And it's going to
do it one at a time so I can check its
work as it as it goes along. Now, I can
already see a lot of places where I want
to improve this process a little bit and
make it a little bit more specific to to
to my world of building Ruby on Rails
apps. You know, for example, I'll
probably start to incorporate my
instrumental components library into
this where I'll instruct it to use my
components and my front-end designs and
things in the projects that it that it
builds out. This is just an example, so
I'm foregoing that for now. You know, as
it goes along, it's going to finish the
the task and then it's actually going to
go back to our task list and it's going
to mark it off as completed as it goes
along. Okay, so it did finish task 1.1
and it updated our task list. It it
marked that off as complete. You know, I
find that sometimes when I'm when I'm
using this process, instead of just
saying like go to the next one, I might
say like do the next three, you know,
all in one shot and I start to, you
know, step back, maybe go grab a coffee
or take a walk, and then I come back and
another part of my project is already
built out. So, you know, this is a
really a really exciting way of of
building. Just to show you, I have like
another version of this project going
forward that I was doing earlier. I got
all the way up to to like midway through
step three. And if I run the server on
that, you know, this is still sort of
early on in this project, but as you can
see, it it actually did start to build
out like a task list. And you know, you
know, I I think the next step up was to
was to make it like drag and drop. So
not super impressive just yet because
it's still early on. This is really more
about the process, right? So, you know,
going from 1.0 up to 3.4 probably took
about an hour. Of course, I'm still kind
of learning my way through this whole
workflow. But again, this is just
something that I can continue to craft
and use and bring more order to the
chaos that that has been vibe coding.
And this feels like a more professional
way of of doing this in the real world.
And that's why I believe this is going
to be the new normal. So, this is taking
that like agent mode into that new
professional way of building software.
So, I'll wrap it up here, but I am going
to be posting a lot more videos on this
new normal way of building with AI vibe
coding at a professional level. So, if
you have any questions about this,
things that you're wondering about, you
know, drop them in the comments. I'll
definitely cover it in an upcoming
video. I have an upcoming workshop, so
drop a comment and I'll get you in on
that. Make sure you're subscribed. Let's
build some stuff.